a few years ago I bought a bow and 10
arrows online it arrived and I was
utterly baffled by how to assemble it
after an hour on multiple YouTube videos
it somewhat resembled a bow so I thought
let's shoot an arrow I'm not going to
show this because it exhibits gross
negligence on my part but I missed the
Target and it went straight through a
wall and out the other side promptly I
thought that's enough of that and I put
the bow in the cup
that's until now it's always bothered me
that I've never actually learned to use
this thing so because this can be rather
dangerous if done incorrectly I thought
it' best to solicit some help I met
Steven Bryson through climbing but he
happens to be a competitive bearb Archer
and Coach he's also the Scottish bearb
indoor and outdoor champ and the
Scottish tour champ 2024 I met up with
Steven at a proper range and with his
help I learned the basics of how to
assemble the bow how to hold it how to
aim and we're ready to start so now with
a proper range to practice I want to see
how quickly I can learn archery first we
need a goal or a milestone Steven
suggested we shoot for a classification
score a classification is used to tell
how archers are progressing there are
nine levels from beginner to Elite but
the first rung on the ladder is called
Archer third class seems like a
reasonable goal here's the deal you
shoot 20 ends of three arrows from 18 M
so that's 60 shots and out of a possible
score of 600 the target is
331 very precise sounds like a piece of
cake let's find out where I am to begin
with okay so this is day one our
Z and then yeah that's it right let's
see let's see if we can get you shooting
[Music]
thing
ah see pinged my nose oh well yes yes
that does happen keep your hand relaxed
nice cor your M keep pulling that's it
[Music]
so did I hit the target a taller you've
hadit a few yeah you shot more on the
target than off the
target so are you happy with that uh not
really
no yes dude I'm surprisingly physical um
like this one here I just felt like I
just couldn't hold the ball steady you
think shoo so far oh no it's been really
good yeah no like I mean you you managed
to hit the gold a few times when you
when you had the grouping around there
that was really good yeah um I mean
consistency is key and then after that
you you work on the little little
details well but yeah no as a beginner
you should be proud I mean not seeing
anyone else
but all right how did I get on first
session well out of a possible score of
600 I scored
232 that's an average of 3.86 per Arrow
so that's a full 99 points shy of the
goal of
331 also I was shooting from 50 m rather
than 18 M so we got a lot of work to do
so let's get practicing I'm confused oh
stringles that
way I've made an but now it's like
really tightly yeah yeah yeah movies do
this all the time I wouldn't film it
I've got a quiver and everything this
[Music]
time with Steven standing right next to
me talking me through everything I have
to do that was actually pretty good come
up come
an
S the scoring was strong in fact for the
first 10 ends I was on track to achieve
my target
[Music]
score
nice but this game is all about
consistency and 60 arrows well that's a
lot no I almost the last
ID have no idea what the drawing though
and then a mess at the
bottom so that's it so I shot
292 points out of a potential 600 so
that's less than half my average Arrow
was
4.87 so there you go Stephen do you
think that's pretty good or bad it's a
good Baseline it's a good Baseline so I
especially For What second session yeah
second session so that's uh that's that
is
awesome this is the first time stringing
my bow without
Steven so all by myself I need to string
this right I think this is how you do
[Music]
it does that look about
right right today I reckon I'm good
enough to go for my go goal which is 331
which is only an average Arrow of
5.53 so you only have to get like a blue
every time so I don't need to try to be
amazing I just need to try to not be
I think it look it was a t no I'm
taking the T cuz I can see the hole
that's the rule
this is not good enough need to step
up R 23 that's what I'm talking
[Music]
about perfect yellow which is 19 that's
good enough yeah 19 is good
[Music]
enough black right we need to recover
from that that's my first Miss of the of
the
round for yeah we it's over now I think
we're
done so I've started making a mess if my
shots and this popped up which I
normally don't have but I know that when
I start getting this problem that um
that's when my shooting starts going
wrong and people are going to say oh why
don't you wear your rist card I don't
like it okay I don't like wearing the
risk card so
biss the slipping through my fingers
right here so we need an average of 6.2
for all six
SS basically we need six
sevens one don't stress
it I'm mentally check out I'm done
with boss it was a good run it was a
good
run I blew it that M I could have you
know what I
[Music]
mean blew it blew it I was I was like on
target coming in after 3 days of
shooting there was a clear pattern
emerging for the first 30 arrows I'm
cruising well above the target average
Arrow of five and a half and then at the
halfway point I just absolutely B it and
throw away the
score
balls damn damn it seems like a
combination of fatigue and the pressure
of scoring high that gets to me I also
seem to be unable to recover after a
really bad shot I'm not sure archery is
a sport for me
it's it enrages me when I shoot bad yeah
I have to do sports that don't make me
angry that's why I hate golf I hate golf
this is very golf likee all about
staying calm even though you're Furious
that you just shot three zeros hopefully
day four will be stronger
[Music]
we're not doing well at all here this is
not
good how can those be like consecutive
shots this is my first shot zero almost
missing the target entirely and then
straighten the bullseye for I would say
that's not a good grouping uh
[Music]
overall so
irritating most annoying sport I I've
ever tried just like when it slaps your
arm and it duffs up the arrow it's just
so irritating and and you you you like
go through the motions to make that not
happen and then you still do it like
what don't know what I'm doing wrong
still achieve it if I get six tens in a
row so like it's not completely lost
I've still got high
[Music]
hopes sake man like I was on target to
the end and now it's now it's end 18 and
I just completely cocked that up so my
worst round yet so we're just getting
worse and
worse clearly frustration is getting the
better of me here I think the pressure
of the score was weighing too heavily on
me what I really needed was a practice
session with no scores no pressure just
a bit of fun okay I have always wanted
to do this obviously can't do it with a
real person so we're using Isabella here
I've always wanted to find out now that
I'm half decent at H archery how many
times will Isabella die for me to hit
the Apple just once I reckon it's going
to be a lot what do you reckon James um
at least at least 100 wait okay I re I'm
going to aim high and just try and bring
it down so hopefully like I just start
getting the Apple but we'll see let's
find out how many times I think she
going to die 20 times
[Music]
okay
oh that's super
[Music]
close oh my
God that is ous look that's the first
shot that's the second shot I don't
think she would have died once she would
have been absolutely UT fine the biggest
thing I changed from the first session
to the second session was which I am
using to aim now I am right eyed this is
my dominant eye the right eye but I'm
left-handed so this is how I shoot my
ball and if I'm aiming with the right
eye everything's just skew with because
I'm not aiming down the line of the
arrow I'm kind of aiming a little bit
off from the advice of Steven he
recommended I switch aiming with the
left eye the left my left eye is not
very sharp I didn't realize how blind I
am but it's actually pretty blurry
however the arrows are much more On
Target when I aim with this eye so
left-handed aim with the left eye
right-handed aim with the right eye
forget about which eye is your dominant
eye I also had a problem with the arrows
flying like that or like that like they
weren't flying straight through the air
like that they were kind of On Target
but they were like upper down which
would cause problems um so what Steven
told me to do was to experiment with
like my position on the string like
whether it's right with my hand on the
string whether it's right up here or
right down there and I came up with like
this tiny little measurement technique I
do where I do something like that and I
get about that distance and that seemed
to immediately fix that sort of fishtail
effect and have the arrow just fly
nicely in an arc straight onto the
target so those are two things that I've
done that I've made a huge huge
difference to how close I am to the
Target close
[Music]
W that's so
bad this fun session was exactly what I
needed in addition to blowing off steam
it proved to me that I can be accurate
and on occasion accurate I now knew that
my problem wasn't in my accuracy but
rather in dealing with the pressure and
maintaining composure till the end of
the round I just needed to chill out my
next round I was feeling confident in my
ability to keep it together for 60
arrows so remember to score 331 over 60
arrows which is my goal I need an
average score of
5.53 per Arrow or
better right
H here we go
[Music]
again that's how we want to start the
end that is extremely good
shooting W what a start
[Music]
this is good this is this this is more
like what I
need I've got a good feeling about this
one we're on a roll we are way above
Target right now all I have to do is
shoot this good or even even average
would do from here on out cuz we are we
are absolutely cruising right now
like this has got to be the round
right mon I'm on
fire I'm on fire right now this has got
to be the Run don't get too cocky it's
in the bag it's done Michael we don't
get
now it starts to happen it starts to
crumble this is when all starts to go
downhill oh
dear a 52 and a zero what I've learned
about archery is it's not about how well
you shoot it's about how well you
recover from this
garbage zero cool slipping away
what I need to do is rapidly I don't
need to improve cuz we're still actually
ahead I just need to stop losing so many
points so quickly I just need to be
average for the rest of the round but
it's really hard like my head's starting
to go I'm starting to worry I can't do
it and uh things are all starting to
fall apart I need to get a grip
[Music]
nervous yeah yeah right on right on the
edge that is not good
enough I'm going to blow it right at the
end again
all I need to do is not up and we'll be
okay but I just missed one and scored
like 10 or something three arrows which
is just not good
enough it's the final end all I need to
do is score seven out of potential
30 surely I can't this up if I miss I I
could screw I could mess this up I could
miss three times oh all I need is a a
seven so easy but I know I'm going
[Music]
to oh
perfect oh great
shot right let's finish up nice and
Strong 9
3 1 gives me an ending of three
337 the go the goal was 331 so that'll
do me
yeah
yes
yes that was a brutal one and 1/ half
hours of just pure concentration I don't
think I'll ever do this again it's
emotionally too
intense right let's go and get a cup of
tea this episode is sponsored by
brilliant in case you haven't heard of
brilliant brilliant is an Interactive
Learning platform where you learn by
doing they have thousands of interactive
lessons in maths data analysis
programming and AI brilliant is a
learning app that helps you build a
daily learning habit and you know me I
love trying to get a little bit better
at something every day each of
brilliant's lessons is filled with
Hands-On problem solving that lets you
interactively play with Concepts this
helps you build critical thinking skills
through problem solving not memorization
which clearly in my opinion is the most
effective way to learn and with their
mix of engaging problems competitive
features and daily encouragement you
won't fall into a frustration pit
brilliant will keep you motivated and on
track something I wanted to highlight
was Brilliance programming courses which
are a super easy way to build your
programming foundations and real world
applications you can start building
programs on day one with their built-in
drag and drop editor you'll learn to
break down complex problems into
manageable chunks of code and develop an
understanding for Computer Logic as you
design and debug real programs all of
brilliant's content is made by an
award-winning team of teachers
researchers and professionals from MIT
Caltech Juke Microsoft and Google so you
know you're getting a quality learning
experience so whether you're studying
for an exam brushing up on existing
knowledge or just learning so you can
better understand AI brilliant has you
covered so go to brilliant. or/ mikeb to
try everything brilliant has to offer
for a full 30 days for free and by
following that link you can also get 20%
off the premium annual subscription
thank you all very much for watching
I'll see you next
time trust really nice Apple
[Music]